Preliminary Inventory to the Sam Tanenhaus Papers, 1901-1998.
Hoover Institution Archives
Sam Tanenhaus Papers,
1901-1998
97029
Tanenhaus, Sam.
69 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes 32.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, correspondence, trial transcripts, memoranda, notes, and printed matter, relating to the life of Whittaker Chambers and to the Alger Hiss espionage case. Used as research material for the book by Sam Tanenhaus, Whittaker Chambers: A Biography (New York, 1997). Includes letters by Chambers.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1997.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Chambers, Whittaker.; Hiss, Alger.; Espionage, Russian--United States.; Communism--United States.; Communism.; United States--Politics and government.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation)
Container List
- Sam Tanenhaus, Whittaker Chambers (Box 1-13.)
  - Drafts
  - Galleys (Box 14.)
- Sam Tanenhaus, draft articles
- Sam Tanenhaus, draft articles (Box 15.)
- Sam Tanenhaus, draft articles (Box 16.)
- Notebooks
- United States vs. Hiss trial transcript, 1949 November (Box 17.)
  - Volumes 1-6
  - Volumes 7-10 (Box 18.)
- United States vs. Hiss trial transcript, 1949 June. Microfilm (4 reels) (Box 19.)
- Whittaker Chambers deposition transcripts
  - 1948
  - 1948-1949 (Box 20.)
- Whittaker Chambers correspondence (Box 21-22.)
- Whittaker Chambers-Ralph de Toledano correspondence (Box 23.)
- Whittaker Chambers chronological file (Box 24.)
  - 1900-1929
  - 1930-1938 (Box 25.)
  - 1939-1945 (Box 26.)
  - 1946-1948 (Box 27.)
  - 1948-1949 (including trial coverage) (Box 28.)
  - 1949 (including trial coverage) (Box 29.)
  - 1950-1952 (including trial coverage) (Box 30.)
  - 1952 (including trial coverage and Witness) (Box 31.)
  - 1952-1961 (including Witness) (Box 32.)
  - 1962-1991 (including Cold Friday, Odyssey of a Friend, and Ghosts on the Roof) (Box 33.)
- Whittaker Chambers subject file
  - Background
  - Biographical miscellany
  - Genealogy
  - Homosexuality
  - Naval intelligence involvement, Alleged
  - Poetry
  - Psychopathic personality, Alleged
  - Residences (Box 34.)
  - Russian knowledge
  - Soviet Union visit, Alleged
  - Time articles
  - Time salary
  - Translations
- General subject file (Box 35.)
  - Aaron, Daniel
  - Abt, John
  - Acheson, Dean
  - Adams, Jeff
  - Adler, Mortimer J.
  - Adler, Nathan
  - Adler, Solomon
  - Agee, James
  - Alsop, Joseph
  - Amerasia
  - American Committee for Cultural Freedom
  - Ames, Aldrich
  - Andrews, Bert
  - Appell, Donald
  - Archival repositories
  - Arendt, Hannah
  - Arts Student League of New York
  - Asimow, Morris
  - Auden, W. H.
  - Aurthur, Robert Alan
  - Bachrach, Marion
  - Bakunin, Mikhail
  - Baltimore (Md.)
  - Baltimore documents. See also Pumpkin papers
  - Bang, Frank and Henry (Box 36.)
  - Bannerman, R. L.
  - Barkham, John M.
  - Barmine, Alexander
  - Barnes, Joseph
  - Barzun, Jacques
  - Bedacht, Max
  - Beer, Thomas
  - Beichman, Arnold
  - Bell, Daniel
  - Bell, James A.
  - Bellow, Saul
  - Bentley, Elizabeth
  - Beriia, Lavrentii
  - Berle, Adolf A.
  - Bernard, Viola
  - Bernstein, Leonard
  - Bill [pseud.]
  - Billikopf, J.
  - Billings, J. S.
  - Billington, James H.
  - Binger, Carl
  - Black [pseud.] (Box 37.)
  - Blankenhorn, Heber
  - Bloor, Ella Reeve
  - Blount, Bob
  - Boerger, Ruth. See also Ikal, Arnold
  - Bohlen, Charles E.
  - Book and Magazine Guild
  - Book jackets
  - Brecht, Bertolt
  - Brenner, Anita
  - Brinkley, Alan
  - Brooks, John
  - Brooks, Win
  - Browder, Earl
  - Buckley, William F., Jr.
  - Budenz, Louis Francis
  - Bullitt, William C.
  - Bullock, Alan
  - Burck, Jacob
  - Burnham, James
  - Buttenwieser, Helen
  - Bykov, Boris
  - Byrnes, James F.
  - Cairncross, John
  - Cantwell, Robert
  - Carmon, Walt (Box 38.)
  - Caro, Robert A.
  - Carpenter, David
  - Carr, Robert K.
  - "Castle," Fort Lee, N.J.
  - Catlett family
  - Catling, Patrick Skene
  - Cerf, Bennett
  - Chamberlain, John
  - Chambers, Ellen and John
  - Chambers, Esther Shemitz
  - Chambers, James S.
  - Chambers, Jay
  - Chambers, Laha Whittaker
  - Chambers, Richard
  - Cheney, Lynne
  - Cherniss, Ruth M.
  - China
  - Christ Church (Lynbrook, N.Y.)
  - Clark, Eleanor
  - Clay, Lucius D.
  - Cleveland, Richard
  - Clubb, O. Edmund
  - Coe, Frank
  - Coe, Robert
  - Cold War
  - Collins, Henry H., Jr.
  - Columbia University
  - Commager, Henry Steele (Box 39.)
  - Communism and anti-communism
  - Communist International archives
  - Conant, James B.
  - Concealed Enemies (Television program)
  - Condon, Edward U.
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations
  - Conquest, Robert
  - Cook, Fred J.
  - Cooke, Alistair
  - Coolidge, Calvin
  - Coplon, Judith
  - Corson, William R. and Robert T. Crowley
  - Cort, David
  - Costello, John
  - Counterattack
  - Cowley, Malcolm
  - Craig, Bruce
  - Crichton, Robert
  - Cronin, John F.
  - Crosley, George [pseud.]
  - Cross, Claude B.
  - Crouch, Paul
  - Cullison, Alan
  - Currie, Lauchlin
  - Dailes, Ida (Box 40.)
  - Daily Worker
  - Danahy, Jack
  - Darling, Maus V.
  - Darrach, Brad
  - Davidow, Larry
  - Davidson, Ben
  - Davis, Hope Hale
  - Davis, Richard Harding
  - Dawnkaski, Rodney J.
  - De Toledano, Ralph
  - Detzer, Dorothy
  - Dewey, John
  - Diamond, Sigmund
  - Dies, Martin
  - Diggins, John P.
  - Djilas, Milovan
  - Doherty, Maura S.
  - Doriss, Robert
  - Dos Passos, John
  - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor
  - Draper, Theodore
  - Drexel Institute of Art, Science and Industry
  - Duggan, Laurence
  - Dulles, Allen
  - Dulles, John Foster
  - Eagleton, Clyde (Box 41.)
  - East Hampton [N.Y.] Star
  - Eastman, Max
  - Edith and Evelyn (maids)
  - Edman, Irwin
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D.
  - Elistratova, A.
  - Ellen, Dorothea
  - Elson, Robert T.
  - Emery, Andree
  - Endore, Guy
  - Erskine, John
  - Fadiman, Clifton
  - Fairbank, John King
  - Fansler, Thomas
  - Farago, Ladislas
  - Farrell, James T.
  - Ferry, Elinor
  - Fiedler, Leslie
  - Field, Frederick V.
  - Field, Noel
  - Field, Richard H.
  - Film and Photo League
  - Fischer, Louis
  - Fischer, Ruth
  - Fitzgerald, Robert
  - Fixx, Calvin
  - Flanagan, Hallie
  - Fones, John Scott
  - Forster, Clifford
  - Foster, William Z.
  - Fountain, Plum
  - Fox, John (Box 42.)
  - Frank, Jerome
  - Frankfurter, Felix
  - Freeman, Joseph
  - Fried, Richard M.
  - Friedberg, Judith
  - Fromkin, David
  - Garlin, Sender
  - Gassner, John
  - Gay Street (New York, N.Y.)
  - Gitlow, Benjamin
  - Glasser, Harold
  - Glazer, Nathan
  - Gold, Mike
  - Goldman, Emma
  - Goldwater, Walter
  - Gordievsky, Oleg
  - Gottfried, Manfred
  - Gouzenko, Igor
  - Great Britain. Foreign Office
  - Gregory [pseud.]
  - Griffith, Thomas
  - Gross, Babette
  - Gruin, Frederick
  - Grunwald, Henry Anatole
  - Gumpert, Martin
  - Gunther, Gerald
  - Hadden, Briton (Box 43.)
  - Halberstam, David
  - Halper, Albert
  - Halperin, Maurice
  - Hamilton, James W.
  - Harry S. Truman Library
  - Hartz, Louis
  - Harvard Progressive
  - Havel, Vaclav
  - Haywood, William D.
  - Hebert, F. Edward
  - Henderson, Loy
  - Henry [pseud.]
  - Herald, Leon
  - Herbert [pseud.]
  - Herbst, Josephine
  - Hersey, John
  - Hicks, Granville
  - Hindus, Milton
  - Hiss, Alger
    - Chronological
    - Biographical (Box 44.)
    - Residences
    - Department of State records
    - Federal Bureau of Investigation records
    - Trial defense records (Box 45.)
    - Miscellaneous
  - Hiss, Bosley
  - Hiss, Donald
  - Hiss, Priscilla
  - Hiss, Tony
  - Hobson, Thayer
  - Hobson, Timothy
  - Hofstadter, Richard
  - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, Jr.
  - Home School (Racine, Wis.)
  - Hook, Sidney
  - Hoover, J. Edgar
  - Horowitz, Helen Lefkowitz
  - Howe, Irving
  - Huffard, J. Hudson
  - Hughes, Emmet
  - Hughes, Langston
  - Hunt, John
  - Hutchins, Grace
  - Hutchinson, Gertrude
  - Hyde, Douglas
  - Hyland, Thomas
  - Ickes, Harold L.
  - Ikal, Arnold. See also Boerger, Ruth (Box 46.)
  - Ingersoll, Ralph
  - Inslerman, Felix A.
  - Intrator, Michael
  - Isaacson, Walter and Evan Thomas
  - Isserman, Maurice
  - Jackson, Gardner
  - Jacobson, Arvid
  - Jacoby, Russell
  - James, Sidney
  - Jessup, John K.
  - Jessup, Philip C.
  - John Reed Clubs
  - Johns Hopkins News-Letter
  - Josephson, Matthew
  - Jowitt, William Jowitt, Earl
  - Judd, Walter H.
  - Judis, John B.
  - Judt, Tony
  - Kahn, David
  - Kalodny, Hyman
  - Kaplan, Irving
  - Kasenkina, Oksana
  - Kastner, Joseph
  - Katz, Otto
  - Kaufman, Samuel H.
  - Kees, Weldon
  - Kempton, Murray
  - Kennan, George F.
  - Kenner, Hugh
  - Kerr, Barbara (Box 47.)
  - Kilpak, Gilbert
  - Kimball, Penn
  - King, Carol
  - King, William Lyon Mackenzie
  - Kirk, Russell
  - Kirstein, Elinor
  - Klaus, Samuel
  - Klehr, Harvey
  - Klingsberg, Ethan
  - Knapp, Mrs.
  - Knightley, Phillip
  - Koch, Stephen
  - Koestler, Arthur
  - Kohlberg, Alfred
  - Kramer, Charles
  - Krieger, Sam
  - Krivitsky, Walter
  - Kronenberger, Louis
  - Ku Klux Klan
  - Labor Fact Book
  - Lamb, Dean Ivan
  - Lamont, Corliss
  - Lamphere, Robert J.
  - Langer, Elinor
  - Lardner, Ring, Jr.
  - Lasch, Christopher
  - Lasky, Victor
  - Lattimore, Owen
  - Lauterbach, Richard E.
  - Leahy, William D. (Box 48.)
  - Le Carré, John
  - Lee, Essie and Alwyn
  - Left Book Club
  - Levin, David
  - Levine, Isaac Don
  - Levine, Nathan
  - Levitt, Morton and Michael
  - Lewis, Edward E.
  - Lewis, Richard F.
  - Lieber, Maxim
  - Liebling, A. J.
  - Lipman, Samuel
  - Lippmann, Walter. See also Reed, John
  - Lock, Owen A.
  - Long Island Railroad
  - Loomis, Robert D.
  - Lore, Ludwig
  - Lovestone, Jay
  - Lowenthal, John
  - Lozowick, Louis
  - Luce, Clare Boothe
  - Luce, Henry
  - Luce, Henry R.
  - Lukacs, John
  - Lumpkin, Grace
  - Lynbrook (N.Y.)
  - Lyons, Eugene (Box 49.)
  - McCarran, Patrick A.
  - McCarthy, Joseph R.
  - McCarthy, Mary
  - Macdonald, Dwight
  - McDonald, John
  - McDermott, Walsh
  - McGohey, John F. X.
  - McLean, E. C.
  - MacLeish, Archibald
  - Macleod, Norman
  - McManus, Robert Cruise
  - McNaughton, Frank
  - Maddox, Robert James
  - Magil, A. B.
  - Malia, Martin
  - Malraux, André
  - Mann, Thomas
  - Mar Cantabrico (Steamship)
  - Marbury, William L.
  - Marder, Murrey
  - Marsh, Reginald
  - Marshall, Thomas
  - Martin, David
  - Martin, Mary
  - Massing, Hede (Box 50.)
  - Matthews, J. B.
  - Matthews, T. S.
  - May, Geoffrey
  - May, Henry F.
  - Medina, Harold R., Jr.
  - Meet the Press (Radio program)
  - Merton, Thomas
  - Meyer, Frank S.
  - Miller, Isidore
  - Miller, Merle
  - Milosz, Czeslaw
  - Milwaukee (Wis.)
  - Milwaukee Sentinel
  - Minster, Leon
  - Moren, Mark
  - Morningside
  - Morris, Richard
  - Morris, Robert
  - Morrow, Felix
  - Morton, Robinson
  - Mosher, Steven W.
  - Moss, Howard
  - Mullady, Frances
  - Mundt, Karl E.
  - Murphy, Frank
  - Murphy, Raymond E.
  - Murphy, Thomas F.
  - Murray, Henry A.
  - Murrow, Edward R.
  - Musmanno, Michael A.
  - Mussey, Barrows
  - Nash, George
  - National Review (Box 51.)
  - Navasky, Victor
  - Nearing, Scott
  - Neils, Patricia
  - Nelson, Eleanor
  - Newberry Library
  - New Deal
  - New London (Conn.)
  - New Masses
  - New York Times
  - Nicholson, Margaret Mary
  - Nicolaevsky, Boris
  - Niebuhr, Reinhold
  - Nisbet, Robert
  - Nitze, Paul H.
  - Nixon, Richard M.
  - Nobile, Philip
  - Nock, Albert Jay
  - Noda, Hideo
  - Norton, Robert C.
  - Norton-Taylor, Duncan
  - Nye, Gerald P.
  - Oak, Liston (Box 52.)
  - O'Brien, Conor Cruise
  - O'Neill, William L.
  - Osborne, John
  - Osman, Ralph
  - Palmer, A. Mitchell
  - Parmet, Herbert S.
  - Partisan Review
  - Patterson, Henry C.
  - Pearson, Drew
  - Pegler, Westbrook
  - Pells, Richard H.
  - Pennoyer, Robert
  - Pennsylvania
  - Perlo, Victor
  - Peterborough (N.H.)
  - Peters, J.
  - Peters, Paul
  - Petran, Tabitha
  - Philby, Kim
  - Phillips, William
  - Pigman, William Ward
  - Pilat, Oliver
  - Popular Front
  - Pornographic comics
  - Port Huron Statement
  - Post, Richard
  - Powell, Webster
  - Powers, Thomas
  - Poyntz, Juliet Stuart (Box 53.)
  - Prange, Gordon W.
  - Pressman, Lee
  - Proletarian literature
  - Publications in legal history
  - Pulitzer, Joseph
  - Pumpkin papers. See also Baltimore documents
  - Pumpkin Papers Irregulars
  - Quakers
  - Racine (Wis.)
  - Racusin, Mr.
  - Rae, Nicol C.
  - Rahv, Philip
  - Rand School of Social Science
  - Reed, John and Walter Lippmann (Box 54.)
  - Regler, Gustav
  - Regnery, Henry
  - Reno, Franklin Victor
  - Reno, Philip
  - Reston, James
  - Reuben, William A.
  - Richler, Mordecai
  - Riesel, Victor
  - Rilke, Rainer Maria
  - Rochester, Anna
  - Roesch, Patricia Divver
  - Rolfe, Edwin
  - Romerstein, Herbert
  - Roose, Roz (Box 55.)
  - Rorty, James
  - Rosenberg, Julius and Ethel
  - Rosenbliett, Philip
  - Ross, J. C.
  - Ross, Nathaniel
  - Rossiter, Clinton
  - Roth, Henry
  - Roth, Samuel
  - Round Robin group
  - Rukeyser, Muriel
  - Rumrich, Guenther Gustave
  - Rush, Jacob
  - Russian famine relief
  - Sacco, Nicola and Bartolomeo Vanzetti
  - Sandino, Augusto
  - Saperstein, Harold I.
  - Sayre, Francis B.
  - Scammell, Michael
  - Schapiro, Meyer
  - Schlamm, William S.
  - Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr.
  - Schmahl, Horace
  - Schmidt, Maria
  - Schrecker, Ellen W.
  - Shachtman, Max
  - Shemitz, Reuben B.
  - Shils, Edward
  - Shotwell, James T.
  - Shoyet, Samuel
  - Silverman, Abraham George
  - Silvermaster, Nathan Gregory
  - Singer, Kurt D. (Box 56.)
  - Smedley, Agnes
  - Smith, Jessica
  - Smith, John Chabot
  - Smith, Mardi
  - Smith, W. Marvin
  - Solow, Herbert
  - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr
  - Sorel, Georges
  - Sorge, Richard
  - Soule, Edmund F.
  - South Side Observer (Rockville Centre, N.Y.)
  - Soviet archives
  - Soviet Union (Box 57.)
  - Sperber, Manès
  - Spier, Franklin
  - Spying
  - Standley, William H.
  - Starobin, Joseph R.
  - State of the Union messages
  - Statute of limitations
  - Stearns, Harold E.
  - Steffens, Lincoln
  - Sterling, Dorothy
  - Stettinius, Edward R., Jr.
  - Stevenson, Adlai E.
  - Stoessel, Fredric
  - Stone, I. F.
  - Stone, William
  - Strachey, John
  - Straight, Michael
  - Stripling, Robert
  - Strout, Richard L.
  - Stryker, Lloyd
  - Sudoplatov, Pavel
  - Sulzberger, C. L.
  - Sversky, Leon
  - Sveshnikov, Vladimir
  - Swan, Patrick
  - Syracuse University
  - Szanto, Bela
  - Taft, Robert A.
  - Tamer, Paul
  - Tamiment Institute
  - Tanner, Louise
  - Taylor, Telford
  - Teachout, Terry (Box 58.)
  - Technology
  - Theoharis, Athan G.
  - Tilghman, James Donnell
  - Time Foreign News Department
  - Toynbee, Arnold J.
  - Tresca, Carlo
  - Trilling, Diana
  - Trilling, Lionel
  - Truman, Harry S.
  - Tuchman, Barbara
  - Two Worlds
  - Tytell, Martin
  - Ulanovskaia, Nadezhda
  - Ulanovskii, Aleksandr
  - Underground
  - United Nations
  - United States. Agricultural Adjustment Administration
  - United States. Central Intelligence Agency (Box 63.)
  - United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities
  - United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on the Judiciary. Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws
  - United States. Dept. of State
  - United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation
  - University of Texas
  - Valtin, Jan
  - Vandenberg, Arthur H.
  - Van Doren, Mark
  - Vega, Marylois Purdy
  - Venona documents (Box 64.)
  - Vezzana, Nicholas S.
  - Viereck, Peter
  - Volkogonov, Dmitrii
  - Volkov, Isaac
  - Volta Place (Washington, D.C.)
  - Von Mehren, Robert B.
  - Wadleigh, Henry Julian
  - Wagner, Charles A.
  - Wald, Alan
  - Waldman, Louis
  - Waldorf Conference
  - Walton, William
  - Ware, Harold
  - Ware, Susan
  - Ware group
  - Warshow, Robert
  - Weaver, Richard M.
  - Wechsler, James A.
  - Weinberger, Eliot
  - Weinstein, Allen (Box 65.)
  - Welles, Sam
  - Welles, Sumner
  - Werfel, Franz
  - Wertenbaker, Charles
  - West, Rebecca
  - Westminster (Md.)
  - Weyl, Nathaniel
  - White, Harry Dexter
  - Whittaker, Charles (Box 66.)
  - Whittaker, David
  - Whittaker, Mary
  - Wiedersum, Roy
  - Wilde, Oscar
  - Wilhelm, Warren
  - Willert, Paul
  - Wills, Garry
  - Wilson, Edmund
  - Wilson, H. Hubert
  - Winchell, Walter
  - Winslow, Anne
  - Winter, Ella
  - Witt, Nathan
  - Wolfe, Bertram D.
  - Woodley Estate (Washington, D.C.)
  - Woodstock typewriter
  - Workers School
  - Wright, Peter
  - Yale University Press
  - Younger, Irving
  - Zablodowsky, David
  - Zeligs, Meyer A. (Box 67.)
  - Zolan, Henry
  - Zukofsky, Louis
  - Zysman, Dale
- Unsorted
- Unsorted (Box 68-69.)
- Oversize copyflow from Soviet archives microfilm (Box 59-62.)